Kathryn Kananen

Summary: 5 years working experience, 2 post education, in bioinformatics and computational biology. My research interests include population genetics with a focus on structural variation, specifically transposable elements, in biomedical research and their relationship with treatments. Strong genetics background with a love for designing, solving biological problems, and exploring all parts of the research process. Combined with skills for workflow development, knowledge of computational tools, and ways to make new tools, I look forward to solving and improving medical treatments.

Experience

OSTOR-ASTOR Project

2020-2022

- Lead developer on harmonization pipeline development.
 - RNASeq, WES, variant calling, annotation, Snakemake, pip, template management systems, docker, environment control,
 - o Minor role in Keycloak and Kubernetes and setup
- Lead developer on visualization development and data management of ORIEN Avatar Project.
 - Pancancer genetic quality control, clinical data quality control and ingest, sequences quality control and ingest, cBioPortal development.
- Tool Development Recontig.
- Research and analysis consults.
 - working with Nanopore reads, used EBV genome assembly with Nanopore.
- Daily work on remote cluster.

Hufford Labs

2015-2019

- Bioinformatics in maize populations.
 - Population structure, dynamic scripting, using computational tools for analysis.
- Programmed in Python, R, and Bash.
- Bi-Weekly presentations.
- Work with HPC system.
- Field and lab work.
 - o DNA isolations, pollinations, phenotype measurements, etc.

Education

MSc Applied Bioinformatics

Cranfield University

2019-2020

- Group thesis Bulk Segregant Analysis software creation (Java)
- *Ind. Thesis* R package expansion VarGen
- Graduated with GPA 4.0

B.S. in Bioinformatics and Computational Biology

Iowa State University 2015-2019

Activities of interest

2022-Present
2017-2018
2015 - 2018
2016

Other Qualifications

- Knowledge of multiple programming languages Python (6yrs), Bash (3.5yrs), R (2yr), and Java (1.5yrs).
- Works in Unix environment natively; works on Linux daily.
- Has working knowledge of HPC systems.
- Work on various gene-mapping techniques for software dev of statistical implementation.
- Worked with large genomic datasets (vcf, fasta, fastq, maf, etc). for the past 5years both academically and for research.
- Very used to data formatting, cleaning, and exploration using R and python.
- Is an advanced GitHub and git user.

Literature

- Asad, S., Damicis, A., Heng, Y., Kananen, K., Collier, K., & Adams, E. et al. (2022).
 Association of Body Mass Index and Inflammatory Dietary Pattern with Breast Cancer Pathologic and Genomic Immunophenotype in the Nurses' Health Study. https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-1598621/v1
- Asad, S., Kananen, K., Mueller, K., Symmans, W., Wen, Y., & Perou, C. et al. (2022). Challenges and Gaps in Clinical Trial Genomic Data Management. *JCO Clinical Cancer Informatics*, (6). https://doi.org/10.1200/cci.21.00193
- Hufnagel, D., Kananen, K., Glaubitz, J., de Jesuś Sánchez-González, J., Doebley, J., & Hufford, M. (2021). Evidence for Multiple Teosinte Hybrid Zones in Central Mexico. https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.02.11.430632